DAVID SONTAG: OK, so
then today's lecture
is going to be about data set
shift, specifically how one can
be robust to data set shift.
Now this is a topic that
we've been alluding to
throughout the semester,
and the setting
that I want you to be
thinking about is as follows.
You're a data scientist
working at, let's say,
Mass General Hospital.
And you've been very careful
in setting up your machine
learning task to make sure that
the data is well specified.
The labels that you're trying
to predict are well specified.
You train on your training data.
You test it on a held out set.
You see that the model
generalizes well.
You do chart review
to make sure what
you're predicting
is actually what
you think you're predicting.
And you even do prospective
deployment, where you then
let your machine
learning algorithm drive
some clinical decision
support, and you
see things are working great.
Now what?
What happens after this stage,
when you go to deployment?
What happens when
your same model
is going to be used
not just tomorrow
but also next week, the
following week, the next year?
What happens if your model,
which is working well
at this one hospital--
then there's
another institution,
say maybe Brigham Women's
Hospital or maybe UCSF
or some rural hospital
in the United States
wants to use the same model.
Will it keep working
in this short term
to the future time period
or in a new institution?
That's the question which
we're going to be talking
about in today's lecture.
And we'll be talking
about how one
could deal with data set shift
of two different varieties.
The first variety is adversarial
perturbations to data.
The second variety
is the data that
changes for natural reasons.
Now the reason why
it's not at all obvious
that your machine learning
algorithm should still
work in this setting is because
the number one assumption
we make when we do
machine learning
is that you're
training distribution.
You're training data is drawn
from the same distribution
as your test data.
So if you now go to a setting
where your data distribution
has changed, even if you've
computed your accuracy using
your holdout data
and it looks good,
there's no reason
that should continue
to look good in this new setting
where the data distribution has
changed.
A simple example of what it
means for data distribution
to change might be as follows.
Suppose that we
have as input data
and we're trying to predict
some label which maybe meant
something like y is if a patient
has or will be newly diagnosed
with type 2 diabetes.
And this is an example which we
talked about when we introduced
risk stratification.
You learn a model
to predict y from x.
And now, suppose you
go to a new institution
where their definition of
what type 2 diabetes means
has changed.
For example, maybe they don't
actually have type 2 diabetes
coded in their data.
Maybe they only
have diabetes coded
in their data, which is lumping
together both type 1 and type 2
diabetes-- type 1 being what's
usually a juvenile diabetes
and is actually a very distinct
disease from type 2 diabetes.
So now the notion of what
diabetes is different.
Maybe the use case is
also slightly different.
And there's no
reason, obviously,
that your model which was used
to predict type 2 diabetes
would work for that new label.
Now this is an example
of a type of data
set shift which is, perhaps
for you, kind of obvious.
Nothing should work in
this setting, right?
Because here, the distribution
of p of y given x changes.
Meaning even if you have
the same individual,
your distribution py given x--
and let's say the distribution
p of 0 and the
distribution p of y
given x in p 1, where
this is one institution,
this is another institution.
These now are two
different distributions
if the meaning of the
label has changed.
So for the same person, there
might be different distribution
over what y is.
So this is one type
of data set shift.
And a very different
type of data
set shift is where we assume
that these two are equal.
And so that would,
for example, rule out
this type of data set shift.
But rather what changes is p of
x from location 1 to location
2, OK?
And this is the type of data set
shift which will be focused on
in today's lecture.
It goes by the name
of covariant shift.
And let's look at two
different examples of that.
The first example would be of
an adversarial perturbation.
And so you've all seen the
use of convolutional networks
for image
classification problems.
This is just one illustration
of such an architecture.
And with such an
architecture, one
could then attempt to do all
sorts of different object
classification or image
classification tasks.
You could take as input
this picture of a dog which
is clearly a dog, right?
And you could modify
it just a little bit.
Just add in a very
small amount of noise.
What I'm going to
do is I'm now going
to create a new image which
is that original image.
Now with every single
pixel, I'm going
to add a very small epsilon in
the direction of that noise.
And what you get out
is this new image,
which you could stare at
it however long you want.
You're not going to be
able to tell a difference.
Basically, to the
human eye, these two
look exactly identical.
Except when you take your
machine learning classifier,
which is trained on
original unperturbed data,
and now apply it
to this new image
it's classified as an ostrich.
And this observation
was published
in a paper in 2014 called
Intriguing Properties of Neural
Networks.
And it really kickstarted
a huge surge of interest
in the machine
learning community
on adversarial perturbations
to machine learning.
So asking questions, if you
were to perturb inputs just
a little bit, how does that
change your classifiers output?
And could that be used to attack
machine learning algorithms?
And how can one
defend against it?
By the way, as an
aside, this is actually
a very old area of
research and even back
in the land of
linear classifiers,
these questions
had been studied.
Although I won't get
into it in this course.
So this is a type of data
set shift in the sense
that what we want is that this
should still be classified
as as a dog, right?
So the actual label
hasn't changed.
We would like this
distribution over the labels
given the perturbed into it
to be slightly different.
Except that now, that sort
of distribution of inputs
is a little bit
different because we're
allowing for some noise to be
added to each of the inputs.
And in this case, the noise
actually isn't random,
it's adversarial.
And towards the end
of today's lecture,
I'll give an example
of how one can actually
generate the adversarial image,
which can change the crossfire.
Now the reason
why we should care
about these types of
things in this course
are because I expect that
this type of data set shift--
which is not at all
natural, it's adversarial--
is also going to start showing
up in both computer vision
and non computer vision
problems in the medical domain.
There was a nice paper
by Sam Philipson,
Andy Beam, and
Zack Cohen recently
which presented
several different case
studies of where these
problems could really
arise in healthcare.
So for example, here
what we're looking at
is an image
classification problem
arising from dermatology.
You're given as input an image.
For example, you would like
that this image be classified
as an individual having
a particular type of skin
disorder nevus, and this
other image melanoma.
And what one can see is that
with a small perturbation
of the input, one
can completely swap
the label that would be assigned
to it from one to the other.
And in this paper
which we're going
to post as optional
readings for today's course,
they talk about how one
could maliciously use
these algorithms for benefit.
So for example, imagine that
a health insurance company now
decides in order to reimburse
for a expensive biopsy
of a patient's skin,
a clinician or nurse
must first take a
picture of the disorder
and submit that picture
together with the bill
for the procedure.
And imagine now that
the insurance company
were to have a machine
learning algorithm be
an automatic sort of check.
Was this procedure actually
reasonable for this condition?
And if it isn't, it
might be flagged.
Now a malicious user could
perturb the input such
that it would, despite
the patient having
perhaps even completely
normal looking skin,
nonetheless be classified by
a machine learning algorithm
as being abnormal in
some way, and thus
perhaps could get reimbursed
by that procedure.
Now obviously this is an example
of a nefarious setting, where
we would then hope that such
a individual would be caught
by the police, sent to jail.
But nonetheless, what we
would like to be able to do
is build checks and balances
into the system such
that that couldn't
even happen, right?
Because to a human,
it's kind of obvious
that you shouldn't be able
to trick anyone with such
a very minor perturbation.
So how do you build
algorithms that
could also be not
tricked as easily
as humans wouldn't be tricked?
AUDIENCE: For any
of these examples,
did the attacker need
access to the network?
And is there a way to
do it if they didn't?
DAVID SONTAG: So the question
is whether the attacker needs
to know something about
the function that's
being used for classifying.
There are examples of both what
are called white box and black
box attacks where
in one setting,
you have access to the function,
and other settings you don't.
So both have been studied
in the literature,
and there are results
showing that one
can attack in either setting.
Sometimes you might need
to know a little bit more.
Like for example,
sometimes you need
to have the ability to query
the function a certain number
of times.
So even if you don't know
exactly what the function is,
if you don't know the weights
of the neural network,
as long as you can query
it sufficiently many times
you'll be able to construct
adversarial examples.
That would be one approach.
Another approach would be maybe
we don't know the function,
but we know something
about the training data.
So there are ways to go about
doing this even if you don't
perfectly know the function.
Does that answer your question?
So what about a
natural perturbation?
So this figure is just
pulled from lecture 5
when we talked about
non stationarity
in the context of
risk stratification.
Just to remind you,
here the x-axis is time.
The y-axis is different types
of laboratory test results
that might be ordered.
And the color denotes how
many of those laboratory
tests were ordered in a certain
population at a point in time.
So what we would expect to see
if the data is was stationary
is that every row would
be a homogeneous color.
But instead what we see is
that there are points in time--
for example, a few months
interval over here--
when suddenly it looks like, for
some of the laboratory tests,
they were never performed.
That's most likely
due to a data problem
or perhaps the feed of data from
that laboratory test provider
got lost.
There were some
systems problems.
But there are also going
to be settings where,
for example, a
laboratory test is never
used until it's suddenly used.
And that may be because
it's a new test that
was just invented or
approved for reimbursement
at that point in time.
So this is an example
of non stationarity,
and of course this could also
result in changes in your data
distribution, such as what
I described over there,
over time.
And the third example
is when you then
go across institutions, when
of course both the language
that might be used--
think of a hospital
in the United States
versus a hospital in China.
The clinical notes will be
written in completely different
languages.
That would be an extreme case.
And a less extreme case might
be two different hospitals
in Boston where the
acronyms, or the shorthand
that they use for
some clinical terms
might actually be different
because of local practices.
So what do we do?
This is all a setup.
And for the rest of the
lecture, what I'll talk about
is first, very
briefly, how one can
build in population level checks
for has something changed.
And then the bulk
of today's lecture
we'll be talking about how
to develop transfer learning
algorithms and how one
could think about defenses
to adversarial attacks.
So before I show you that
first slide for bullet one,
I want to have a
bit of discussion.
You've suddenly done that thing
of learning a machine learning
algorithm in your
institution, and you
want to know will this algorithm
work at some other institution.
You pick up the phone.
You call up your
collaborating data scientist
at that other institution.
What are the questions that
you should ask them in order
to try and understand will your
algorithm work there as well?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: What kind of
lab test information
they collect regularly.
DAVID SONTAG: So
what type of data
do they have on their
patients, and do they
have similar data types
or features available
for their patient population?
Other ideas, someone who
hasn't spoken in the last two
lectures.
Maybe someone in
the far back there,
people who have
their computer out.
Maybe you with your hand
in your mouth right there.
Yeah, you with the glasses on.
Ideas?
AUDIENCE: Can you
repeat the question?
DAVID SONTAG: You want me
to repeat the question?
The question was as follows.
You learn your machine learning
algorithm at some institution,
and you want to apply it
now in a new institution.
What questions should you
ask of that new institution
to try to assess whether your
algorithm will generalize
to that new institution?
AUDIENCE: I guess it depends on
your problem you're looking at.
Are there possible differences
in your population?
If you're acquiring data
with particular tools,
what are the differences in
the tools that are being used?
Are their machines
calibrated differently?
Do they use different
techniques to acquire the data?
DAVID SONTAG: All
right, so let's
break down each of the
answers that you gave.
The first answer
that you gave was
are there differences
in the population.
Someone else now, what would
an example of a difference
in a population?
Yep.
AUDIENCE: Age distribution,
where they have younger people
in Boston versus central
Massachusetts, for example.
DAVID SONTAG: So you
may have younger people
in Boston versus older people
over in central Massachusetts.
How might a change
in age distribution
affect your ability of your
algorithm to generalize?
AUDIENCE: It's possible that
health patterns for younger
people are very different
than that for older people.
Perhaps some of
the diseases there
are more prevalent in
populations that are older.
DAVID SONTAG: Thank you.
So sometimes we might expect
a different set of diseases
to occur for a younger
population versus older
population, right?
So type 2 diabetes,
hypertension-- these
are diseases that are often
diagnosed when individuals
are 40s, 50s, and older.
If you have people
who are in their 20s,
you don't typically
see those diseases
in a younger population.
And so what that means is
if your model, for example,
was trained on a population
of very young individuals,
then it might not be able to--
suppose you're doing something
like predicting future cost,
or so something which
is not directly tied
to the disease itself.
The features that are predictive
of future cost in a very
young population might be
very different from features
for predictors of cost in
a much older population,
because of the
differences in conditions
that those individuals have.
Now the second
answer that was given
had to do with calibration
of instruments.
Can you elaborate
a bit about that?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
So I was thinking related
in the colonoscopy space.
So if, in that space, you're
collecting videos of colons,
and so you could have
machines that are
calibrated very differently.
Let's say different light
exposure, different camera
settings.
But you also have the
GIs, and the physicians
have different techniques as
to how they explore the colon.
So the video data itself is
going to be very different.
DAVID SONTAG: So the
example that was given
was of colonoscopies
and data that might
be collected as part of that.
And the data that
could be collected
could be different for
two different reasons.
One, because the
actual instruments
that are collecting the data,
for example imaging data,
might be calibrated a
little bit differently.
And second reason might be
because the procedures that
are used to perform that
diagnostic test might be
different in each institution.
Each one will result in slightly
different biases to the data,
and it's not clear that
an algorithm trained
on one type of procedure
or one type of instrument
will generalize to another.
So these are all great examples.
So when one reads a paper
from the clinical community
on developing a new risk
stratification tool, what
you will always
see in this paper
is what's known as table one.
Table one looks a
little bit like this.
Here, I've pulled
one of my own papers
that was published in
JAMA Cardiology for 2016,
where we looked at how to try
to find patients with heart
failure who are hospitalized.
And I'm just going to walk
through what this table is.
So this table is
describing the population
that was used in the study.
At the very top, it says these
are characteristics of 47,000
hospitalized patients.
Then what we've done is,
using our domain knowledge,
we know that this is a
heart failure population.
And we know that there are
a number of different axes
that differentiate patients
who are hospitalized
that have heart failure.
And so we enumerate over
many of the features
that we think are critical to
characterizing the population,
and we give
descriptive statistics
on each one of those features.
You always start with things
like age, gender, and race.
So here, for example, the
average age was 61 years old.
This was, by the way,
NYU Medical School.
50.8% female, 11.2%
black African-American.
17.6% of individuals
were on Medicaid,
which was the state
provided health
insurance for either disabled
or lower income individuals.
And then we looked at quantities
like what types of medications
were patients on.
42% of inpatient patients
were on something
called beta blockers.
31.6% of outpatients
were on beta blockers.
We then looked at things
like laboratory test results.
So one could look at the
average creatinine values,
the average sodium values
of the patient population,
and this way describe what
is the population that's
being studied.
Then when you go to
the new institution,
that new institution receives
not just the algorithm,
but they also receive
this table one
that describes the
population which
the algorithm was learned on.
And they could use that together
with some domain knowledge
to think through questions
like what I elicited
from you in our discussion.
So we could think,
does it make sense
that this model will generalize
to this new institution?
Are the reasons
why it might not?
And you could do that
even before doing
any prospective evaluation
on the new population.
So almost all of you
should have something
like table one in your
project write ups,
because that's an important
part of any study in this field,
describing what is the
population that you're
doing your study on.
You agree with me, Pete?
AUDIENCE: I would just add
that table one, if you're
doing a case control study,
will have two columns that
show the distributions
in both populations,
and then a p value of how
likely those differences are
to be significant.
And if you leave that out, you
can't get your paper published.
DAVID SONTAG: I'll just
repeat Pete's answer
for the recording.
This table is for a
predictive problem.
But if you're thinking about
a causal inference type
problem where there is a notion
of different intervention
groups, then you'd
be expected to report
the same sorts of things
but for both the case
population, the people
who received treatment
one, and the control
population, people
who received treatment zero.
And then you would be
looking at differences
between those populations as
well, at the individual feature
level, as part of
the descriptive
statistics for that study.
AUDIENCE: Just to identify
[INAUDIBLE] between hospitals,
is it sufficient to do
t test on those tables?
DAVID SONTAG: To see
if they're different.
So they're always going
to be different, right?
You go to a new
institution, it's
always going to look different.
And so just looking to see
has something changed--
the answer is always
going to be yes.
But it enables a conversation,
to think through.
And then you might use
some of the techniques
that Pete's going to talk about
next week on interpretability
to try and understand.
What is the model
actually using?
Then you might ask,
oh, OK, the model
is using this thing which
makes sense in this population
but might not make sense
in another population.
And it's these two
things together
that make the conversation.
Now this question
has really come
to the forefront in recent
years in close connection
to the topic that Pete
discussed last week on fairness
in machine learning.
You might ask if a classifier
is built in some population,
is it going to generalize
to another population
if that population that it was
learned on was very biased.
For example, it might have
been all white people.
You might ask, is
that classifier
going to work well
in another population
that might perhaps
include people
of different ethnicities.
And so that has led to a concept
which was recently published.
This working draft that I'm
showing the abstract from
was just a few weeks ago
called Datasheets for Datasets.
And the goal here
is to standardize
the process of eliciting
the information, what
is it about the data set that
really played into your model.
And so I'm going to
walk you through,
very briefly, just
a couple of elements
of what a example data set for
a data sheet might look like.
This is too small
for you to read,
but I'll blow up one
section in just a second.
So this is a data
sheet for a data
set called studying
face recognition
in an unconstrained environment.
So it's for a computer
vision problem.
There are going to be
number of questionnaires
which this paper that I
pointed you to outlines.
And you, as the model developer,
go through that questionnaire
and fill out the answers to it.
So including things about
motivation for the data set
creation, composition,
and so on.
So in this particular instance,
this data set labeled faces
in the wild was created to
provide images that study face
recognition in
unconstrained settings,
where image character vision
characteristics such as pose,
illumination, resolution, and
focus cannot be controlled.
So it's intended to be
real world settings.
Now one of the most
interesting sections
of this report that one should
release with the data set
has to do with how was the
data pre processed or cleaned.
So for example
for this data set,
it walks through the
following process.
First, raw images were
obtained from the data set,
and it consisted of
images and captions that
were found together with
that image in news articles
or around the web.
Then there was a face detector
that was run on the data set.
Here were the parameters of the
face detector that were used.
And then remember, the goal
here is to study face detection.
And so one has to know how
were the labels determined.
And how would one, for
example, eliminate if there
was no face in this image.
And so there, they describe
how a face was detected and how
a region was determined to not
be a face in the case that it
wasn't.
And finally, it describes
how duplicates were removed.
And if you think
back to the examples
we had earlier in the
semester from medical imaging,
for example, and
pathology and radiology,
similar data set constructions
had to be done there.
For example, one would
go to the PAC system
where radiology
images are stored.
One would decide which images
are going to be pulled out.
One would go to
radiography reports
to figure out how do we
extract the relevant findings
from that image, which
would give the labels
for that learning task.
And each step there
will incur some bias,
which one needs to
describe carefully in order
to understand what
might the bias be
of the learned classifier.
So I won't go into more
detail on this now,
but this will also be
one of the suggested
readings for today's course.
It's a fast read.
I encourage you to go through it
to get some intuition for what
are questions we might want
to be asking about data sets
that we create.
And for the rest of
the lecture today, I'm
now going to move on to
some more technical issues.
We're doing machine
learning now.
The populations
might be different.
What do we do about it?
Can we change the
learning algorithm
in order to hope that your
algorithm might transfer better
to a new institution?
Or if we get a little bit of
data from that new institution,
could we use that
small amount of data
from the new institution
or a point in the future
to retrain our model to
do well in that slightly
different distribution?
So that's the whole field
of transfer learning.
So you have data drawn from one
distribution, on p of x and y,
and maybe we have a
little bit of data
drawn from a different
distribution, q of x, y.
And under the covariance
shift assumption,
I'm assuming that q x
comma y is equal to q
of x times p of
y given x, namely
that the conditional
distribution of y given x
hasn't changed.
The only thing that
might have changed
is your distribution over x.
So that's what the covariant
shift assumption would assume.
So suppose that we
have some small amount
of data drawn from the
new distribution q.
How could we then
use that in order
to perhaps retrain our
classifier to do well
for that new institution?
So I'll walk through four
different approaches to do so.
I'll start with
linear models, which
are the simplest to understand.
And then I'll move
on to deep models.
The first approach is something
that you've seen already
several times in this course.
We're going to think about
transfer as a multi task
learning problem,
where one of the tasks
has much less data
than the other task.
So if you remember when
we talked about disease
progression modeling,
I introduced
this notion of
regularizing the weight
vectors so that they could
be close to one another.
At that time, we were
talking about weight vectors
predicting disease
progression at different time
points in the future.
We can use exactly
the same idea here
where you take your linear
classifier that was trained
on a really large corpus.
I'm going to call the weights
of that classifier W old.
And then I'm going to solve a
new optimization problem, which
is minimizing over the weight
w that minimizes some loss.
So this is where your new
training data come in.
So I'm going to assume that
the new training data D is
drawn from the q distribution.
And now I'm going to add on a
regularization that asks that W
should stay close to W old.
Now if D, the data from
that new institution,
was very large then you
wouldn't need this at all.
You would be able to ignore
the cross fire that you learned
previously and just
refit everything
to that new institution's data.
Where something like this
is particularly valuable
is if there's a small
amount of data set shift,
and you only have a very
small amount of labeled data
from that new institution.
Then this would allow you to
change your weight vector just
a little bit, right?
So if this coefficient
was very large,
it would say that the
new W can't be too far
from the old W.
So it would allow
you to shift things
a little bit in order
to do well on the small
amount of data that you have.
If there is a feature which
was previously predictive
but that feature is no longer
present in the new data set,
so for example it's all
identically 0, then of course
the new weight for that feature
is going to be set to 0.
And that weight
you can think about
as being redistributed to
some of the other features.
This make sense?
Any questions?
So this is the simplest
approach to transfer learning.
And before you ever try
anything more complicated,
I always try this.
So the second approach is
also with a linear model.
But here, we're no longer going
to assume that the features are
still useful.
So when you go from
your first institution,
let's say MGH on the
left, you learn your model
and you want to apply it
to some new institution,
let's say UCSF on
the right, it could
be that there are some really
big change in the feature set,
such that the original
features are not
at all useful for
the new feature set.
And a really extreme
example of that
might be the setting
that I gave earlier.
You know, your model's
trained on English,
and you're testing it
out on Chinese, right?
If you used a bag
of words model,
that would be an example
where your model obviously
wouldn't generalize at all
because your features are
completely different.
So what would you
do in that setting?
What's the simplest
thing that you might do?
So you're taking a text
classifier learned in English,
and you want to
apply it in a setting
where the language is Chinese.
What would you do?
Translate, you said.
There was another answer?
AUDIENCE: Train RNN.
DAVID SONTAG: Train
an RNN to do what?
Oh, so assume that
you have some ability
to do machine translation.
You translate from
Chinese to English.
It has to be in that
direction because
your original classifier
was trained in English.
And then your new function
is the composition
of the translation and the
original function, right?
And then you can
imagine doing some fine
tuning if you had a
small amount of data.
Now the simplest
translation function
might be just to use
a dictionary, right?
So you look up a
word, and if that word
has an analogy in
another language,
you say OK, this
is the translation.
But there are always going to
be some words in your language
which don't have a
very good translation.
And so you might imagine that
the simplest approach would
be to translate, but
then to just drop out
words that don't
have a good analog
and force your classifier
to work with, let's say,
just the shared vocabulary.
Everything we're
talking about here
is an example of a
manually chosen decision.
So we're going to manually
choose a new representation
for the data, such that we
have some amount of shared
features between the source
and target data sets.
So let's talk about
electronic health record.
By the way, the slides that
I'll be presenting here
are from a paper
published in KDD
by Jan, Tristan, your instructor
Pete, and John Guttag.
So you have two
electronic health
records, electronic
health record 1,
electronic health record 2.
How can things change?
Well, it could be that the same
concept in electronic health
record 1 might be mapped
to a different encoding,
so that's like an English
to Spanish type translation,
in electronic health record 2.
Another example
of a change might
be to say that some
concepts are removed.
Like maybe you have
laboratory test results
in electronic health
record 1 but not
in electronic health record 2.
So that's why you see
an edge to nowhere.
There might be new concepts.
So the new institution
might have new types of data
that the old
institution didn't have.
So what do you do
in that setting?
Well, one approach,
we could say OK, we
have some small amount of
data from electronic health
record 2.
We could just train
using that and throw away
your original data from
electronic health record 1.
Of course, if you only
have a small amount
of data from the
target to distribution,
then that's going to be a very
poor approach because you might
not have enough data
to actually learn
a reasonable enough model.
A second obvious
approach would be OK,
we're going to just train on
electronic health record 1
and apply it.
And for those concepts that
aren't present anymore,
so be it.
Maybe things will
work very well.
A third approach, which we
were alluding to before when
we talked about
translation, would
be to learn a model just on
the intersection of the two
features.
And what this work
does is they say
we're going to manually
redefine the feature set
in order to try to find as
much common ground as possible.
This is something
which really involves
a lot of domain
knowledge, and I'm
going to be using this
as a point of contrast
from what I'll be talking about
in 10 or 15 minutes, where
I talk about how one could
do this without that domain
knowledge that we're
going to use here.
OK?
So the setting that
we looked at is
one of predicting outcomes
such as in hospital mortality
or length of stay.
The model which is going to be
used is a bag of events model.
So we will take a patient's
longitudinal history up
until the time of prediction.
We'll look at different
events that occurred.
And this study was
done using PhysioNet.
So in Mimic, for example, events
are encoded with some number.
5814 might correspond
to a CVP alarm.
1046 might correspond
to pain being present.
25 might correspond to the drug
heparin being given, and so on.
So we're going to create one
feature for every event, which
is encoded with some number.
And we'll just say
1 if that event
has occurred, 0 otherwise.
So that's the representation
for a patient.
Now when one goes to this
new institution, EHR2,
the way that events are encoded
might be completely different.
One won't be able to just
use the original feature
representation, and that's
the English to Spanish example
that I gave.
But instead, what
one could try to do
is come up with a new feature
set where that feature
set could be derived from each
of the different data sets.
So for example since each
one of the events in Mimic
has some text description
that goes with it--
event 1 corresponds
to ischemic stroke.
Event 2, hemorrhagic
stroke, and so on.
One could use that English
description of the feature
to come up with a way to map
it into a common language.
In this case, the
common language
is the UMLS, the
United Medical Language
System that Pete talked
about a few lectures ago.
So we're going to now say, OK,
we have a much larger feature
set where we've now
encoded ischemic stroke
as this concept,
which is actually
the same ischemic
stroke, but also
as this concept and
that concept which
are more general versions
of that original one, right?
So this is just general stroke.
And it could be multiple
different types of strokes.
And the hope is that even if
some of these more specific
ones don't show up in the
new institutions' data,
perhaps some of the more general
concepts do show up there.
And then what you're going
to do is learn your model now
on this expanded
translated vocabulary,
and then translate it.
And at the new
institution, you'll
also be using that
same common data model.
And that way, one hopes
to have much more overlap
in your feature set.
And so to evaluate
this, the author
has looked at two different
time points within Mimic.
One time points was when the
Beth Israel Deaconess Medical
Center was using electronic
health record called CareVue,
and the second time point
was when that hospital
was using a different
electronic health
record called MetaVision.
This is an example actually
of non stationarity.
Now because of them using two
different electronic health
records, then codings
were different
and that's why
this problem arose.
And so we're going
to use this approach,
and we're going to then
learn a linear model
on top of this new encoding
that I just described.
And we're going to compare the
results by looking at how much
performance was lost due
to using this new encoding,
and how well we generalize
from the source task
to the target task.
So here's the first
question, which
is how much do we lose by
using this new encoding?
So as a comparison
point for looking
at predicting in
hospital mortality,
we'll look at what is the
predictive performance
if you're to just use an
existing, very simple risk
score called the SAP score.
And that's this red line
where the y-axis here
is the area under the
ROC curve, and the x-axis
is how much time
in advance you're
predicting, so the
prediction gap.
So using this very
simple score SAP,
get somewhere between 0.75 and
0.80 area under the ROC curve.
But if you were to use all
of the events data, which
is much, much richer than
what went into that simple SAP
score, you would get
the purple curve, which
is SAPS plus the events
data, or the blue curve
which is just the events data.
And you can see you
can get substantially
better predictive
performance by using
that much richer feature set.
The SAP score has the advantage
that it's easier to generalize,
because it's so simple.
Those feature elements
one can trivially
translate to any new EHR, either
manually or automatically,
and thus it will always
be a viable route.
Whereas this blue
curve, although it
gets better predictive
performance,
you have to really worry about
these generalization questions.
The same story happens in both
the source task and the target
task.
Now the second question
to ask is, well,
how much do you lose when you
use the new representation
of the data?
And so here, looking at again
both EHRs, what we see first
in red is the same
as the blue curve
I showed in the previous slide.
It's using SAPS plus the item
IDs, so using all of the data.
And then the blue
curve here, which
is a bit hard to see
but it's right there,
is substantially lower.
So that's what
happens if you now
use this new representation.
And you see that you
do lose something
by trying to find a
common vocabulary.
The performance
does get hit a bit.
But what's particularly
interesting is
when you attempt to generalize,
you start to see a swap.
So now the colors are
going to be quite similar.
Red here was at the
very top before,
so red is using the original
representation of the data.
Before, it was at the very top.
Shown here is the training error
on this institution, CareVue.
You see there's so
much rich information
in the original
feature set that it's
able to do very good
predictive performance.
But once you attempt
to translate it--
so you train on CareVue,
but you test on MetaVision--
then the test performance shown
here by this solid red line
is actually the worst
of all of the systems.
There's a substantial
drop in performance
because not all
of these features
are present in the new EHR.
On the other hand, the
translated version--
despite the fact that it's
a little bit worse when
evaluated on the source--
it generalizes much better.
And so you see a significantly
better performance
that's shown by this
blue curve here when you
use this translated vocabulary.
There's a question.
AUDIENCE: So when you
train with more features,
how do you apply the model if
not all the features are there?
DAVID SONTAG: So you assume
that you have come up
with a mapping from the
features in both of the EHRs
to this common feature
vocabulary of QEs.
And the way that this mapping is
going to be done in this paper
is based on the
text of the events.
So you take the text based
description of the event,
and you come up with a
deterministic mapping
to this new UMLS-based
representation.
And then that's
what's being used.
There's no fine
tuning being done
in this particular example.
So I consider this to be a very
naive application of transfer.
The results are exactly what you
would expect the results to be.
And obviously, a lot of work
had to go into doing this.
And there's a bit of creativity
in thinking that you should use
the English based
description of the features
to come up with the automatic
mapping, but sort of the story
ends there.
And so a question
which all of you
might have is how
could you try to do
such an approach automatically?
How could we automatically
find new representations
of the data that are likely
to generalize from, let's say,
a source distribution to
a target distribution?
And so to talk about
that, we're going
to now start thinking through
representation learning
based approaches, of which
deep models are particularly
capable.
So the simplest approach
to try to transfer
learning in the context of,
let's say, deep neural networks
would be to just chop
off part of the network
and reuse some internal
representation of the data
in this new location.
So the picture looks a
little bit like this.
So the data might
feed in the bottom.
There might be a number
of convolutional layers,
some fully connected layers.
And what you decide
to do is you're
going to take this model that's
trained in one institution,
you chop it at some layer.
It might be, for example, prior
to the last fully connected
layer.
And then you're going to
take the new representation
of your data.
Now the representation
of the data
is what you would
get out after doing
some convolutions followed by
a single fully connected layer.
And then you're going to
take your target distribution
data, which you might only
have a small amount of,
and you learn a simple model on
top of that new representation.
So for example, you might
learn a shallow classifier
using a support
vector machine on top
of that new representation.
Or you might add in
a couple more layers
of a deep neural network and
then fine tune the whole thing
end to end.
So all of these have been tried.
And in some cases, one
works better than another.
And we saw already one example
of this notion in this course,
and that was when Adam
Yalla spoke in lecture 13
about breast cancer
and mammography.
Where in his approach,
he said that he
had tried both taking a
randomly initialized classifier
and comparing that to what
would happen if you initialized
with a well known image net
based deep neural network
for the problem.
And he had a really
interesting story that he gave.
In his case, he had enough
data that he actually
didn't need to initialize
using this pre trained model
from ImageNet.
If he had just done a random
initialization, eventually--
and this x-axis,
I can't remember.
Maybe it might be hours
of training or epochs.
I don't remember.
It's time.
Eventually, the
random initialization
gets to a very
similar performance.
But for his particular
case, if you
were to do a initialization with
ImageNet and then fine tune,
you get there
much, much quicker.
And so it was for the
computational reason
that he found it to be useful.
But in many other applications
in medical imaging,
these same tricks become
essential because you just
don't have enough data
in the new test case.
And so one makes use of,
for example, the filters
which one learns from
an ImageNet task which
is dramatically different from
the medical imaging problems.
And then using those
same filters together
with sort of a new set of
top layers in order to fine
tune it for the problem
that you care about.
So this would be
the simplest way
to try to hope for a common
representation for transfer
in a deep architecture.
But you might ask, how would
you do the same sort of thing
with temporal data,
not image data?
Maybe data that's from
a language or data
from timed series of
health insurance claims.
And for that, you
really want to be
thinking about recurrent
neural networks.
So just remind you,
recurrent neural network
is a recurrent
architecture where
you take as input some vector.
For example, if you're
doing language modeling,
that vector might be encoding
just a one hot encoding of what
is the word of that location.
So for example, this
vector might be all zeros
except for the fourth
dimension, which
is 1 denoting that this
word is the word "class."
And then it's fed into
a recurrent unit which
takes previous hidden
states, combines it
with the current input, and
gives you a new hidden state.
And in this way, you read in,
you encode the full input.
And then you might predict,
make a classification
based on the hidden state
of the last timestamp.
That would be a common approach.
And here would be a very simple
example of a recurrent unit.
Here I'm using s to
denote the hidden state.
Often we see h used to
This is a particularly simple
example where there's just
a single non linearity.
So you take your
previous hidden state,
you hit it with some matrix
Wss, and you add that
to the input being hit
by a different matrix.
You now have a
combination of the input
plus the previous hidden state.
You apply non linearity
to that, and you
get your new hidden state out.
So that would be an example
of a typical recurrent unit,
a very simple recurrent unit.
Now the reason why I'm
going through these details
is to point out that the
dimension of that Wsx matrix
is the dimension of the hidden
state, so the dimension of s,
by the vocabulary size
if you're using a one
hot encoding of the input.
So if you have a
huge vocabulary,
that matrix Wss is also
going to be equally large.
And the challenge
that presents is
that it would lead to
over fitting on rare words
very quickly.
And so that's a
problem that could
be addressed by instead using
a low rank representation
of that Wsx matrix.
In particular, you could think
about introducing a lower
dimensional bottleneck
which, in this picture,
I'm noting as xt prime--
which is your original
xt input, which
is the one hot encoding,
multiplied by a new matrix We.
And then your recurrent
unit only takes
inputs of that xt
prime's dimension, which
is k, which might be
dramatically smaller than v.
And you can even think
about each column
of that intermediate
representation We
as a word embedding.
And this is something that Pete
talked to quite a bit about
when we were talking my
natural language processing.
And many of you would have
heard about in the context
of things like word to vec.
So if one wanted to take
a setting, for example,
one institution's data where
you had a huge amount of data,
learn a recurrent neural network
on that institution's data,
and then generalize it
to a new institution,
one way of trying to do that--
if you think about it, what
is the thing that you chop?
One answer might be all you
do is keep the word embedding.
So you might say, OK, I'm
going to keep the We's.
I'm going to translate
that to my new institution.
But I'm going to let the
recurrent parameters--
for example, that
Wss, you might allow
to be relearned for
each new institution.
And so that might
be one approach
of how to use the
same idea that we
had from feed forward
neural networks
within a recurrent setting.
Now all of this is very general.
And what I want to do
next is to instantiate it
a bit in the context
of health care.
So since the time
that Pete presented
the extensions of where to
vec, such as Bert and Elmo--
and I'm not going
to go into them now,
but if you go back to Pete's
lecture from a few weeks
ago to remind yourselves
what those were--
since the time you
presented that lecture,
there are actually
three new papers
that tried to apply this in
the health care context, one
of which was from MIT.
And so these papers all
have the same sort of idea.
They're going to
take some data set.
And these papers all use Mimic.
They're going to
take that text data.
They're going to learn
some word embeddings
or some low dimensional
representations
of all words in the vocabulary.
In this case,
they're not learning
a static representation
for each word.
Instead, these Burt
and Elmo approaches
are going to be learning
what you can think
of as dynamic representations.
They're going to be a
function of the word
and their context on the
left and right hand sides.
What they'll do is then
take those representations
and attempt to use them
for a completely new task.
Those new tasks might
be on Mimic data.
So for example, these two tasks
are classification problems
on Mimic.
But they might also
be on non Mimic data.
So these two tasks are from
classification problems
on clinical tasks that didn't
even come from Mimic at all.
So it's really an
example of translating
what you learn from
one institution
to another institution.
These two data sets
were super small.
Actually, all of these data
sets were really, really small
compared to the
original size of Mimic.
So there might be some hope that
one could learn something that
really improves generalization.
And indeed, that's
what plays out.
So all these tasks are looking
at a concept detection task.
Given a clinical note,
identify the segments of text
within a note that
refer to, for example,
a disorder or a treatment or
something else, which you then,
in a second stage, might
normalize to the ULMS.
So what's really striking
about these results
is what happens when you go
from the left to the right
column, which I'll
explain in a second,
and what happens when
you go top to bottom
across each one of
these different tasks.
So the left column
are the results.
And these results
are an f score.
The results, if you
were to use embeddings
trained on a
non-clinical data set--
or definitely not on Mimic, but
on some other more general data
set.
The second column
is what would happen
if you trained those embeddings
on a clinical data set,
in this case Mimic.
And you see pretty
big improvements
from the general embeddings
to the Mimic based embeddings.
What's even more striking
is the improvements
that happen as you get
better and better embeddings.
So the first row are
the results if you
were to use just word
to vec embeddings.
And so for example, for
the ITB2 challenge in 2010,
you get 82.65 f score using
word to vec embeddings.
And if you use a very
large Burt embedding,
you get 90.25 f
score, f measure,
which is substantially higher.
And the same findings were
found time and time again
across different tasks.
Now what I find really
striking about these results
is that I had tried many of
these things a couple of years
ago, not using Bert
or Elmo but using word
to vec, glove, and fast text.
And what I found is that
using word embedding
approaches for these problems--
even if you threw that in as
additional features on top
of other state of
the art approaches
to this concept
extraction problem--
did not improve
predictive performance
above the existing
state of the art.
However in this paper,
here they used the simplest
possible algorithm.
They used a recurrent
neural network
fed into a conditional
random field
for the purpose of classifying
each word into each
of these categories.
And the features that they
used are just these embedding
features.
So with just the word to
vec embedding features,
the performance is crap.
You don't get anywhere
close to the state of art.
But with the better
embeddings, they actually
improved on the state of
the art for every single one
of these tasks.
And that is without any of the
manual feature engineering.